Welcome to 2026 release wave two launch
edition of
our enhanced financial reporting.
We have three types of features to show
you.
Features for authors, for users, and for
administrators. So, let's get started on
the first, which is for the authors.
Um
basically, we have a bunch of what we
call quality of life features. All the
little things that just makes your life
easier.
Things all the way from discover
uncategorized accounts on the chart of
account, all the way down to previewing
when you are working with row and column
definitions.
The latter is coming in a minor version
of 29, but I'll show you here.
Anyway.
So, when you are on the chart of
accounts page, and if you use account
categories, which you should, in my
opinion, both to make your financial
reporting definitions easier,
also if you're using
Power BI for finance,
both features use categories. Now, if
you add a new GL account and you didn't
categorize it, how do you know?
Well,
now you have an easy way. We added two
new
saved views or list views on chart of
accounts. One called at uncategorized
accounts. You can see that here.
And another one
within this new account 42. Another one
is uncategorized accounts where we are
also showing if you have a missing
subcategory. Because with
categorization, you can categorize and
have subcategories.
So, hopefully this just helps you check
if there was something you were missing,
especially if a financial report is not
really showing the data you expected it
to because you have on card authorized
accounts.
Another thing for the controller or for
the author is how do you track if a
given GL account is being used in
financial report definitions? So the
where used lists as you can see here the
action that has been on the
account card for ages now include data
from which reports would include this
account. So if we click this, we can see
that this particular account is being
used in these two row definitions for
financial reporting.
Switching to row definitions in
financial reporting
if you use
which you probably do
use totaling
lines, then if you have complicated
formulas for the totaling
how do you troubleshoot which accounts
are actually
uh
covered by that filter?
Uh
in an in this new version we are adding
you can see here there's a new fact box
where you can see for the given line
which accounts this filter is including.
If if you take this fact box and
then you can even navigate directly back
to the GL account lists if you want to
dive even further into these accounts.
Now row definitions have um
these filters but actually you can do
the same on a column. So um on a here is
a column definition where we have a GL
account totaling um not probably not
something a lot of users of financial
reporting use but you can do it. And
because we have a totaling field here,
we are also have added the same fact box
showing the GL accounts.
And then this is all this is all part of
the major release, but in here in the
fall there will be some other goodies.
The first is
that you can
preview
the so if you're working on a row or a
column definition, you can set the
corresponding other thing. So if you're
on a row definition, you can set a
default column definition for testing
and for a column definition you can set
a default row definition for testing.
And then there's going to be a test
button so that you don't have to leave
the row or column definition to kind of
see the full report.
So that's the general idea of these
preview
features when you work on the these
definitions.
But wait, there's more. There's always
more.
Also coming in a minor to 29
is
defaulting. So if you work on a row
or column definition
and add the lines of the same type, then
now we're defaulting to that.
Hopefully that makes the data entry
working with definitions much easier.
And we also have a a few other small
things to make the experience
easier.
Now let's
switch to
user features. There's actually just
one,
but a big one, report packs. So what is
that? Well,
it's as simple as you can now run
multiple reports in one go and get a
single PDF. Here in Business Central,
you now have a new menu action called
packages. If you navigate to this,
you can
define a package, a report package, give
it a code, a description, and then start
adding which reports should be part of
that report package. You can even set
um
custom filters on on each of these
wrench entries.
Um and also start and end date filters
because these can also be scheduled.
Um and for this particular choice of uh
the account category overview analysis
and balance sheet, the PDF you get, as
you can see here, contains of five
pages, account categories overview, and
then followed by the capital structure,
and then the balance sheet in one PDF.
You can also schedule these, as I
mentioned. If you go to the top here, uh
the for the schedules, uh you can
schedule a pack. So, the idea is that
maybe each Friday for the team meeting
in the finance team, there's going to be
a pack of reports, and that's been
scheduled, so that lands in your report
inbox
uh in the morning.
Speaking of report inbox, that's
actually part of the administrator
features, we have two things for you.
The first is that we now uh simply set
up change log on all financial report
definitions, not the actual uh log
tables, but everything else. And that
means that your financial reporting
feature is kind of auto
um set up for uh for change log, which
means auditing.
And um here's an example of change log
entries, where I didn't d- do anything,
uh I didn't set up anything. I I just
ran uh some changes to, in this case,
financial report um
definition for account overview, uh
category overview, and the corresponding
road definition and this get locks gets
locked here. You can see my
my user ID Kenny on top of it and that I
did that.
I mentioned the report inbox as part of
the scheduling.
There's now
an API on this as well. So that means
that each of the operations you would
expect
on the report inbox
has their own API.
Just filtering on the new API overview
page to report inbox and you can see
them here. The use cases that maybe when
things are scheduled, let's say the
Friday meeting, maybe you want to kick
off some other automation. Maybe you
want to use some AI to analyze the
report output something and that is now
possible with the new APIs. You can call
them through MCP server, power platform
or any other thing that speaks API.
And that's it. Just one more thing. If
you want to learn more about financial
reporting,
take a look at this AKA link
aka.ms/bcfinanceanalytics
and under that landing page there is
also a landing page for financial
reporting. All right, that's it for now.
I hope you have a great launch edition
with lots of other videos to learn from.
I'm done here. So goodbye from me.